A Guide to the C. Eugene Rowe Papers, c.1961-1987
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
C. Eugene Rowe Papers, c.1961-1987
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1989-035
13.3 cu. ft. 11 boxes
The C. Eugene Rowe Papers include materials created and collected by Rowe relating to Virginia Tech during his tenure on the Board of Visitors (1968-1976). There is also a small group of papers from Rowe's involvement in the Presbyterian church.
Rowe, C. Eugene
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Boxes 1-10 are open for research. Box 11 is contains materials on court cases and access is restricted.
Acquisition Information
The C. Eugene Rowe Papers were donated to Special Collections prior to 1989.
Biographical Note
C. Eugene Rowe was born Northumberland County, Virginia. He attended VPI from 1926-1933, when he graduated with a degree in Business. Beginning in the 1950s, he became active in the Alumni Association. In 1968, he began the first of two successive terms on the Board of Visitors, including 5 years as rector. From 1972-1985, he also served as president and then chairman of the Virginia Tech Foundation. Rowe died in 1987.
Additional resources:
Photograph: http://spec.lib.vt.edu/archives/125th/bov/rectors/Rowe.html. Extended biography: https://www.unirel.vt.edu/history/administration/rowe_c_eugene.html
Scope and Content
The C. Eugene Rowe Papers include materials created and collected by Rowe. The majority of the papers relate to Rowe's time as a member (1968-1976) and rector (1970-1975) of the Board of Visitors and include correspondence, meeting minutes, alumni association topics, events/issues on campus, financial issues, press releases, the Presidential search in 1974, academics at Virginia Tech, and higher education in general. There is also a small group of papers from Rowe's involvement in the Presbyterian church.
Arrangement
The collection is in its original order within the boxes. To make locating materials easier, the contents list below groups files into two series: Professional Papers and Personal Papers. Folder titles were taken from the existing files. Professional Papers includes files relating to Rowe's work for and at the university, between about 1961 and 1987. The smaller set of Personal Papers contains files documenting Rowe's involvement with the Presbyterian Church, dating primarily from the 1960s.
Index Terms
Persons:
Rowe, C. Eugene
Corporate Names:
Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. Alumni Association.; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. Board of Visitors.; Virginia Polytechnic Institute. Board of Visitors.
Subjects:
University Archives; University History; Virginia Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Contents List
- Professional Papers, c.1961-1987
  - "A University at Prayer" (Alfred Payne) (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Addresses of VPI People (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Alumni Association, 1961-1963 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Alumni Association (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Alumni Association, 1965 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Alumni Association, 1967 (Box-folder 1-6 to 1-7)
  - Alumni Association, 1968 (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Alumni Association, 1969 (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Alumni Association, 1970 (Box-folder 1-10)
  - Alumni Association, 1971 (Box-folder 1-11)
  - Alumni Association, 1972 (Box-folder 1-12)
  - Alumni Association, 1973 (Box-folder 1-13)
  - Alumni Association, 1974 (Box-folder 1-14)
  - Alumni Association, 1975 (Box-folder 1-15)
  - Alumni Association, 1976 (Box-folder 1-16)
  - Alumni Association, 1977 (Box-folder 1-17)
  - Alumni Association, 1978 (Box-folder 1-18)
  - Alumni Association, 1981 (Box-folder 1-19)
  - Alumni Association (Box-folder 1-20)
  - Alumni Association, 1986 (Box-folder 1-21)
  - Alumni Association, 1987 (Box-folder 1-22)
  - Appendix to Report of the Nuclear Event of November 2, 1971 (Box-folder 1-23)
  - Association of Governing Boards of Universities and Colleges (Box-folder 1-24)
  - Association of Governing Boards Southern Regional Conference, February 4, 1971 (Box-folder 1-25)
  - Board of Visitors Correspondence, 1962-1967 (Box-folder 1-26)
  - Board of Visitors Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 1-27)
  - Board of Visitors Correspondence, 1970 (Box-folder 1-28)
  - Board of Visitors Correspondence, 1971 (Box-folder 1-29)
  - Board of Visitors Correspondence, 1972 (Box-folder 1-30 to 1-31)
  - Board of Visitors Correspondence, January-May 1973 (Box-folder 2-32)
  - Board of Visitors Correspondence, June-December 1973 (Box-folder 2-33)
  - Board of Visitors Correspondence, 1974 (Box-folder 2-34)
  - Board of Visitors Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 2-35)
  - Board of Visitors Executive Committee (Box-folder 2-36)
  - Board of Visitors Executive Committee Meeting, January 7, 1971 (Box-folder 2-37)
  - Board of Visitors Executive Committee Meeting, June 26, 1974 (Box-folder 2-38)
  - Board of Visitors Meeting, September 12, 1968 (Box-folder 2-39)
  - Board of Visitors Meeting, November 15, 1969 (Box-folder 2-40)
  - Board of Visitors Meeting, January 28, 1970 (Box-folder 2-41)
  - Board of Visitors Meeting, May 4, 1970 (Box-folder 2-42)
  - Board of Visitors Meeting, August 17, 1970 (Box-folder 2-43)
  - Board of Visitors Meeting, November 7, 1970 (Box-folder 2-44)
  - Board of Visitors Meeting, February 21, 1971 (Box-folder 2-45)
  - Board of Visitors Meeting, May 20, 1971 (Box-folder 2-46)
  - Board of Visitors Meeting, July 15, 1971 (Box-folder 2-47)
  - Board of Visitors Meeting, August 16, 1971 (Box-folder 2-48)
  - Board of Visitors Meeting, November 20, 1971 (Box-folder 2-49)
  - Board of Visitors Meeting, January 19, 1972 (Box-folder 2-50)
  - Board of Visitors Meeting, March 24, 1972 (Box-folder 2-51 to 2-52)
  - Board of Visitors Meeting, August 7, 1972 (Box-folder 2-53)
  - Board of Visitors Meeting, November 11, 1972 (Box-folder 2-54)
  - Board of Visitors, Meeting, February 28, 1973 (Box-folder 3-55)
  - Board of Visitors, Meeting, May 12, 1973 (Box-folder 3-56)
  - Board of Visitors, Meeting, August 13, 1973 (Box-folder 3-57)
  - Board of Visitors, Meeting, November 9, 1973 (Box-folder 3-58)
  - Board of Visitors, Meeting, February 1, 1974 (Box-folder 3-59)
  - Board of Visitors, Meeting, May 6, 1974 (Box-folder 3-60)
  - Board of Visitors, Meeting, August 9, 1974 (Box-folder 3-61)
  - Board of Visitors, Meeting, November 22, 1974 (Box-folder 3-62)
  - Board of Visitors, Meeting, February 17, 1975 (Box-folder 3-63)
  - Board of Visitors, Meeting, May 17, 1975 (Box-folder 3-64)
  - Board of Visitors, Meeting, August 12, 1975 (Box-folder 3-65)
  - Board of Visitors, Meeting, November 15, 1975 (Box-folder 3-66)
  - Board of Visitors, Meeting, February 22, 1976 (Box-folder 3-67)
  - Board of Visitors, Meeting, May 15, 1976 (Box-folder 3-68)
  - Board of Visitors, Membership and Nominations (Box-folder 3-69)
  - Board of Visitors, Minutes, 1968-1972 (Box-folder 3-70)
  - Board of Visitors, Minutes, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 3-71)
  - Budgets (Box-folder 3-72)
  - Business College of Advisory Council, 1976-1978 (Box-folder 3-73)
  - Business College of Advisory Council, 1979-1983 (Box-folder 3-74)
  - Business College of Advisory Council, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 3-75)
  - By Laws and Policies, VPI (Box-folder 3-76)
  - Campaign for Excellence (Box-folder 4-77)
  - College Trustee Duties (Box-folder 4-78)
  - Commencement, 1971 (Box-folder 4-79)
  - Commencement, 1972 (Box-folder 4-80)
  - Commencement, 1975 (Box-folder 4-81)
  - Conflict of Interest Forms (Box-folder 4-82)
  - Contracts- T. Marshall Hahn (Box-folder 4-83)
  - Corps of Cadets, Select Committee, 1976 (Box-folder 4-84)
  - Corps of Cadets, Select Committee, 1977 (Box-folder 4-85)
  - Corps of Cadets, Select Committee, 1978, 1980 (Box-folder 4-86)
  - Corps of Cadets, Status Report, November 1, 1980 (Box-folder 4-87)
  - Corps of Cadets, Status Report, November 1, 1980 - Attachments (Box-folder 4-88)
  - Correspondence, 1968-1970 (Box-folder 4-89)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box-folder 4-90)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (January - June) (Box-folder 4-91)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (July- December) (Box-folder 4-92)
  - Correspondence, 1973 (January - May) (Box-folder 4-93)
  - Correspondence, 1973 (June- December) (Box-folder 4-94)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box-folder 4-95)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box-folder 4-96)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box-folder 4-97)
  - Correspondence, 1976-1978 (Box-folder 4-98)
  - Correspondence Concerning Personnel Forms, 1975 (Box-folder 5-99)
  - Correspondence- T. Marshall Hahn (Box-folder 5-100)
  - Correspondence- T.Marshall Hahn (Box-folder 5-101)
  - Correspondence- T.Marshall Hahn, 1972 (Box-folder 5-102)
  - Correspondence- T.Marshall Hahn, June- December 1973 (Box-folder 5-103)
  - Correspondence- T.Marshall Hahn, 1974 (Box-folder 5-104)
  - Correspondence- T.Marshall Hahn's Resignation (Box-folder 5-105)
  - Correspondence- Hahn's Salary (Box-folder 5-106)
  - Correspondence- William Lavery, 1974-1978 (Box-folder 5-107)
  - Correspondence- Rector, Charles W. (Box-folder 5-108)
  - Developement Council (Box-folder 5-109)
  - Developement Council, 1966-1973 (Box-folder 5-110)
  - Developement Council, April 12, 1974 (Box-folder 5-111)
  - Developement Council, April 16 1976 (Box-folder 5-112)
  - Developement Council, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 5-113)
  - Educational Foundation (Box-folder 5-114)
  - Educational Foundation (Box-folder 5-115)
  - Educational Foundation (Box-folder 5-116)
  - Educational Foundation (Box-folder 5-117)
  - Educational Foundation (Box-folder 5-118)
  - Educational Foundation (Box-folder 5-119)
  - Educational Foundation (Box-folder 5-120)
  - Educational Foundation (Box-folder 5-121)
  - Educational Foundation, Board of Directors, 1985 (Box-folder 5-122)
  - Educational Foundation- Funds Evaluation, 1984 (Box-folder 5-123)
  - Educational Foundation- Investment Committee (Box-folder 5-124)
  - Financial Information (Box-folder 6-125)
  - Financial Information (Box-folder 6-126)
  - Founder's Day, April 10, 1973 (Box-folder 6-127)
  - Founder's Day, 1979- T. Marshall Hahn (Box-folder 6-128)
  - General Assembly Commission Higher Education, October 2 1973 (Box-folder 6-129)
  - Hahn Dinner, August 6 1972 (Box-folder 6-130)
  - Hahn Retirement- Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder 6-131)
  - Hokie Club (Box-folder 6-132)
  - Inauguration of John Wilson as President of Washington and Lee, May 19, 1983 (Box-folder 6-133)
  - Lavery, William E.- Biographical Information (Box-folder 6-134)
  - Lavery, William- Presidential Inauguration (Box-folder 6-135)
  - Miscellaneous Meetings (Box-folder 6-136)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder 6-137)
  - Newspaper Clippings Concerning Hahn Resignation (Box-folder 6-138)
  - Omicron Delta Kappa- Alpha Omicron Circle (Box-folder 6-139)
  - Omicron Delta Kappa, Alpha Omicron Circle 1972 (Box-folder 6-140)
  - Planned Gifts Committee (Box-folder 6-141)
  - Planned Gifts Committee (Box-folder 4-142)
  - Planned Gifts Committee (Box-folder 6-143)
  - Presidential Search Committee, 1974 (Box-folder 6-144)
  - Presidential Search Applicants (1974) (Box-folder 6-145)
  - Presidential Search Committee- Correspondence (Box-folder 6-146)
  - Press Release, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 6-147)
  - Press Release, etc., 1971 (Box-folder 6-148)
  - Press Release, 1972 (Box-folder 6-149)
  - Press Release, 1973 (Box-folder 6-150)
  - Press Release, 1974 (Box-folder 6-151)
  - Resignation as Rector (Box-folder 7-152)
  - Reynolds Homestead Dedication, May 24, 1975 (Box-folder 7-153)
  - Ruffner Award (Box-folder 7-154)
  - Second Century Emphasis Panel (Box-folder 7-155)
  - Speech- Administrative Planning Conference, September 12, 1972 (Box-folder 7-156)
  - Speech- Pamplin Hall Dedication, September 20, 1969 (Box-folder 7-157)
  - Speeches (1965-1975, 1983) (Box-folder 7-158)
  - State Commission on Higher Education in Virginia (Box-folder 7-159)
  - State Commission on Higher Education (Box-folder 7-160)
  - State Commission on Higher Education in Virginia. June 28, 1971 (Box-folder 7-161)
  - Statewide Planning in Higher Education Conference, June 7-9, 1972 (Box-folder 7-162)
  - Student Aid Association, 1975-1978 (Box-folder 7-163)
  - Student Government Association (Box-folder 7-164)
  - Student Unrest- Clippings (Box-folder 7-165)
  - Ut Prosim Society (Box-folder 7-166)
  - UVA Graduate School of Business Administration Sponsors (Box-folder 7-167)
  - UVA Graduate School of Business Administration Sponsors 1967-1970 (Box-folder 7-168)
  - College of Veterinary Medicine (Box-folder 7-169)
  - William Preston Society (Box-folder 7-170)
  - Wilson, John D. - Candidacy for President (Box-folder 7-171)
  - Wine Making in Virginia (Box-folder 7-172)
  - YMCA (Box-folder 7-173)
  - Audit Correspondence, 1970s (Box-folder 7-174)
  - Athletics Association Report, 1949 (Box-folder 1-175)
  - VPI Education Foundation Financial Statements, June 30, 1974 (Box-folder 7-176)
  - Investment Services, June 3, 1985 (Box-folder 7-177)
  - Annual Report, June 1985 (Box-folder 7-178)
  - Report on Audit, June 30, 1975 (Box-folder 7-179)
  - Unaudited Financial Statements, June 30, 1973 (Box-folder 7-180)
  - Report on Audit - Dormitory and Dining Hall, 1972 (Box-folder 7-181)
  - Report on Audit - Student Center Fee Revenue, 1972 (Box-folder 7-182)
  - Report on Audit - National Defense Student Loan, 1971 (Box-folder 7-183)
  - Report on Audit - Student Center Fee Revenue, 1974 (Box-folder 7-184)
  - Report on Audit - Student Center Fee Revenue, 1971 (Box-folder 7-185)
  - Report on Audit - Dormitory and Dining Hall, 1971 (Box-folder 7-186)
  - Report on Audit, 1971 (Box-folder 7-187)
  - Audit Correspondence, December 1973 (Box-folder 7-188)
  - Report on Audit - Dormitory and Dining Hall, 1970 (Box-folder 7-189)
  - Report on Audit, 1968 (Box-folder 7-190)
  - Proposed Constitutions and Bylaws, January 1969 (Box-folder 8-191)
  - Virginia Tech Annual Report (Box-folder 8-192)
  - Degrees Conferred (Box-folder 8-193)
  - Financing Virginia's Colleges, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 8-194)
  - Annual Commencements (Box-folder 8-195)
  - Commencement, 1971 (Box-folder 8-196)
  - Resident and Off-Campus Enrollment, !872-1973 (Box-folder 8-197)
  - Report to the Board of Visitors, 1973 (Box-folder 8-198)
  - Report to the Board of Visitors, 1973 (Box-folder 8-199)
  - Virginia Tech Reports (Box-folder 8-200)
  - Virginia Higher Education (Box-folder 8-201)
  - Virginia Plan for Higher Education (Box-folder 8-202)
  - Report to the Board of Visitors, 1974 (Box-folder 8-203)
  - Report to the Board of Visitors, 1975 (Box-folder 8-204)
  - Grade-A Dairy Farm Growth in Virginia, 1975 (Box-folder 8-205)
  - Presidential Search, 1975 (Box-folder 8-206)
  - Faculty Handbooks (Box-folder 8-207)
  - Alumn i Survey, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 8-208)
  - University Policies for Student Life, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 8-209)
  - The Guidon, Virginia Tech Corps of Cadets, 1984 (Box-folder 8-210)
  - Inauguration of William E. Lavery, 1975 (Box-folder 8-211)
  - "On Campus" Newsletter, 1976 (Box-folder 8-212)
  - Competition for Student Services Building, 1983 (Box-folder 8-213)
  - Association of Governing Boards of Universities and Colleges (Box-folder 8-214)
  - Campaign Plan, 1982 (Box-folder 8-215)
  - Budget Report, 1985 (Box-folder 8-216)
  - Summary of Orientation Conference, 1973 (Box-folder 8-217)
  - Livestock Research report, 1975 (Box-folder 8-218)
  - Biennial Report, 1968-1970 (Box-folder 8-219)
  - Governor's Day, September 30, 1966 (Box-folder 9-220)
  - Century Club Certificate, 1970 (Box-folder 9-221)
  - "The University and You" Meeting, September 11-12, 1970 (Box-folder 9-222)
  - A Guide to Professional Development Opportunities, 1975 (Box-folder 9-223)
  - Eight Hundred Colleges Face the Future, 1965 (Box-folder 9-225)
  - Virginia's Private Colleges and Public Interest, 1971 (Box-folder 9-226)
  - The Balancing Act, 1974 (Box-folder 9-227)
  - A Manual for College Trustees, 1965 (Box-folder 9-228)
  - An Inventory of Academic Innovation and Reform, 1973 (Box-folder 9-229)
  - Shared Authority on Campus (Box-folder 9-230)
  - Resources for Urban Schools, 1971 (Box-folder 9-231)
  - Journal of Higher Education, 1971 (Box-folder 9-232)
  - ROTC in Review, 1968 (Box-folder 9-233)
  - Dwight Hamilton Baldwin, 1953 (Box-folder 9-234)
  - AGB Reports, 1969 (Box-folder 9-236)
  - AGB Reports, January - April 1970 (Box-folder 9-237)
  - AGB Reports, May - November 1970 (Box-folder 9-238)
  - AGB Reports, December 1970 - October 1971 (Box-folder 9-239)
  - AGB Reports, January - April 1972 (Box-folder 9-240)
  - AGB Reports, May - December 1972 (Box-folder 9-241)
  - AGB Reports, January - April 1973 (Box-folder 9-242)
  - AGB Reports, May - December 1973 (Box-folder 9-243)
  - AGB Reports, January - April 1974 (Box-folder 9-244)
  - AGB Reports, May - October 1974 (Box-folder 9-245)
  - Carnegie Commission, 1971 (Box-folder 9-246)
  - Carnegie Commission, 1972 (Box-folder 9-247)
  - Carnegie Commission, April - June 1973 (Box-folder 9-248)
  - Carnegie Commission, August - October 1973 (Box-folder 9-249)
  - Artifacts (Box-folder 9-250)
  - Newspapers/Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder 10-259)
  - [FILE RESTRICTED] Court Action Suits (Box 11)
- Personal Papers, c.1960s
  - The Lay Governing Board (Box-folder 9-224)
  - Presbyterian Survey, 1964 (Box-folder 9-235)
  - General Assembly Presbyterian Church Complaint and Appeal (Box-folder 10-251)
  - Church Bulletins and Pamphlets (Box-folder 10-252)
  - Montreat, North Carolina (Box-folder 10-253)
  - Correspondence (Box-folder 10-254)
  - Church Notes (Box-folder 10-255)
  - The Presbyterian Journal, 1964 (Box-folder 10-256)
  - The Presbyterian Outlook, 1964 (Box-folder 10-257)
  - Reports (Box-folder 10-258)